A Guide to the Pleasant Shade Cemetery (Hampton, Va.) records, compiled 2012-2018
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Pleasant Shade Cemetery (Hampton, Va.) records, compiled 2012-2018
The Library of Virginia
54206
1.4 cubic feet (4 boxes)
John Mitchell, Mary Kayaselcuk, and Selma Stewart
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Artistine Mears-Lang, Hampton, Virginia, and Mary Kayaselcuk and Selma Stewart, Newport News, Virginia.
Historical Information
Pleasant Shade Cemetery, comprising over 20 acres, is the oldest and largest public African American cemetery located on the lower Virginia Peninsula. It is a combination of three earlier burial grounds, Mount Zion (1888), Pleasant Shade (1908) and Holly Grove (1918), and contains an estimated 15,000 burials, of which only a portion have been identified. After its owners abandoned the cemetery, Darnell Lang (1954-2024) and Artistine Mears-Lang founded the East End Neighborhood Association to organize volunteer efforts to save and maintain the cemetery. The cemetery has been divided into 14 sections to make identification of burial sites easier. The cemetery is the resting place for many prominent African American leaders of Hampton and Newport News, Virginia, including James A. Fields (1844-1903), member of the Virginia House of Delegates; attorney and social justice pioneer Joseph Thomas Newsome (1869-1942); evangelist Lightfoot Soloman Michaux (1885-1968); and Jessie Menfield Rattley (1929-2001), the first woman and African American to serve on the Newport News City Council and as mayor of Newport News.
Scope and Content
Cemetery records for Pleasant Shade Cemetery, the oldest African American public cemetery on the Virginia Peninsula. Information compiled 2012-2018 by John Mitchell, Mary Kayaselcuk, and Selma Stewart. Provides name and burial information for identified burials in the 14 sections of the cemetery listed by section and by alphabetical order. Includes information on veterans, notable persons, and persons born in the 1800s.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Sections
Series II: Veterans
Series III: 1800s
Series IV: Notables
Series V: Marker surveys
Series VI: Alphabetical
Series VII: Search
Series VIII: General and miscellaneous
Contents List
- Sections., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  - Section 1-Galilee--Maps, photographs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Section 1--Galilee--Burial by row and plot (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Section 1-Galilee--Early births, 1800s, veterans (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Section 2-Shiloh (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Section 3-Ephesus--Map, veterans, burials-verify, 1800s, early briths, notables, blank pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Section 3-Ephesus--Burial by row and plot (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Section 4-Philippi--Veterans, 1800s, clergy, notables (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Section 4-Philippi--Burial by row and plot (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Section 5-Antioch (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Section 6-Beulah (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Section 7-Mt. Carmel (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Section 8-Corinth (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Section 9-Jericho--Maps, photographs, old sheets, statistics, correspondence, copies, blanks, additions (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Section 9-Jericho--Burial by row and plot, revisions and additions (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Section 9-Jericho--Early births, blank sheets, additions, maps (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Section 10-Cyprus (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Section 11-Canaan (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Section 12-Gilead (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Section 13-Gethsemane--Maps, markers, burial by row and plot (rows 1-10) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Section 13-Gethsemane--Burial by row and plot (rows 11-20) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Section 13-Gethsemane--Burial by row and plot (rows 21-28) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Section 13-Gethsemane--Veterans, early births, miscellaneous, maps, early births, 1800s, masons, notables, row 17 (draft) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Section 14-Samaria (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Veterans., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  - Veterans (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 1800s., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  - 1800s--Section 1-Galilee (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1800s--Section 2-Shiloh (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1800s--Section 12-Gilead (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1800s--Section 13-Gethsemane (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1800s--Early birth sheets-blank and Galilee, 1800 sheets-blank (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1800s--Earliest births (Box 2, Folder 14)